From the Treaty of the Treason:
引自叛國罪條款：
In penance for their uprising,each district shall offer up
為使叛亂者贖罪，每個地區每年都要
a male and female between the ages of 12 and 18 at a public 'reaping'.
公開「抽籤」選擇一對年齡 在12-18歲的少年男女作為貢品
These Tributes shall be delivered to the custody of the Capitol.
這些貢品會被送至都城凱匹特監管 (註：凱匹特為施惠國的都城，對旗下12個行政區 具有絕對統治權，是「飢餓遊戲」的始作俑者)
And then transferred to a public arena where they will Fight to the Death, until a lone victor remains.
然後送至競技場，他們將在那裏戰鬥至死 直到剩下最後一名勝利者 （註：競技場，飢餓遊戲每屆都會選擇全新的比賽 場地，由荒廢土地改建而成；比賽後成為旅遊勝地）
Henceforth and forevermore this pageant shall be known as The Hunger Games.
這個盛會自此永遠地被稱為 飢餓遊戲
I think it's our tradition.
我想這是我們的傳統
It comes out of a particularly painful part of our history.
它源於我們國家歷史上極其慘痛的那段經歷
Yes, yes.
是的
But it's been the way we've been able to heal.
但它已經成為使我們能夠治癒痛苦的方式
At first, it was a reminder of the rebellion.
起初，這是對叛亂行為的警示
- It was a price the districts had to pay. - Yes.
- 叛亂地區必須因此而付出代價 - 對
But I think it has grown from that.
但我認為現在更成熟了一些
I think it's something that knits us all together.
這可以讓我們團結在一起
This is your third year as Gamemaker.
作為連續三年的遊戲製作者
What defines your personal signature?
您的座右銘是什麼？
No! No!
不！不！
[DISTRICT 12]
[12區]
It's okay. It's okay. You were just dreaming. You were dreaming.
沒事，別怕，你只是在做夢，一個夢罷了
It was me.
我夢見被選中了
I know. I know. But it's not.
我知道，但是事實不是這樣的
It's your first year, Prim. Your name's only been in there once.
這是你的第一年，普利姆 你的名字只在那出現過一次
They're not gonna pick you.
他們不會選你的
Try to go to sleep.
再去睡會吧
I can't.
我睡不著
Just try. Just try.
試試吧，躺下就睡著了
Deep in the meadow
在草叢深處
Under the willow
在柳樹下
- A bed of grass
- 草墊床
- A soft green pillow
- 軟軟的綠枕頭
You remember that song? Okay.
你還記得這歌？很好
You finish it. I've got to go.
把它唱完，我得出去下
Where?
去哪？
I've just got to go.
我必須得走了
But I'll be back. I love you
不過我會回來的，我愛你
I'll still cook you.
我還是要把你燉了
[DISTRICT BOUNDARY] [NO ACCESS BEYOND THIS POINT]
[區域分界] [禁止通行]
[HIGH VOLTAGE]
[高壓電]
What are you gonna do with that when you kill it?
你打算怎麼獵殺它？
Damn you, Gale! It's not funny!
該死，蓋爾！這並不好笑！
What are you gonna do with a 100-pound deer, Catnip?
對於重達100磅的鹿你還能怎麼辦？凱特尼普 （注:女主角叫Katniss，為印地安語的慈菇之意，是伴水而生的植物， 根部可食用。由於發音類似，蓋爾昵稱她為Catnip，意為貓薄荷）
It's Reaping Day. The place is crawling with Peacekeepers.
今天是抽籤日，到處都是維和部隊
I was gonna sell it to some Peacekeepers.
我本打算把它賣給維和部隊的
Of course you were.
當然
Like you don't sell to Peacekeepers.
就像你不賣給他們似的
No. Not today.
不，不是今天
It was the first deer I've seen in a year. Now I have nothing.
這可是今年我看到的第一頭鹿 現在什麼都沒了
Okay.
好吧
What if they did? Just one year. What if everyone just stopped watching?
如果他們不看了呢？只有一年 假使大家都不看飢餓遊戲了呢？
- They won't, Gale. - What if they did? What if we did?
- 不會的，蓋爾 - 如果他們不看了呢？如果我們不看了呢？
Won't happen.
不會的
You root for your favorites. You cry when they get killed.
你會為自己喜歡的選手加油 一旦被殺你就會哭個不停
- It's sick. - Gale.
- 真噁心 - 蓋爾
If no one watches, then they don't have a game.
如果沒人看，他們就沒這個遊戲
It's as simple as that.
再簡單不過
- What? - Nothing.
- 什麼？ - 沒什麼
- Fine. Laugh at me. - I'm not laughing at you.
- 好吧，你就笑我吧 - 我沒笑你
We could do it, you know?
我們能做到，你知道嗎？
Take off, live in the woods. It's what we do anyway.
離開這，在樹林裏生活，這就是我們要做的
They'd catch us.
他們會把我們抓回來的
Well, maybe not.
也許不會
Cut out our tongues, or worse. We wouldn't make it five miles.
割掉我們的舌頭，甚至更糟 我們跑不出五英里
No, I'd get five miles. I'd go that way.
不，我已經跑出五英里了，我走的那條路
I have Prim, and you have your brothers.
我這還有普利姆，你也有弟弟
They can come, too.
他們可以一起來
Prim in the woods?
讓普利姆到樹林裏生活？
Or maybe not.
也許未必
I'm never having kids.
我沒要過孩子
I might, if I didn't live here.
我也許會要，如果不在這兒生活的話
- But you do live here. - I know, but if I didn't.
- 但你就在這生活 - 我知道，我是說假如
I forgot.
差點忘了
Here.
給
Oh, my God! Is this real?
天吶！真的嗎？
Yeah. Better be. Cost me a squirrel.
當然是真的，我用一個松鼠換的
Happy Hunger Games.
飢餓遊戲快樂
"And may the odds be ever in your favor."
「希望好運永遠站在你這邊」
How many times is your name in today?
今天你名字被用多少次了？
Forty-two.
42次
Guess the odds aren't exactly in my favor.
我看好運並不站在我這邊
Thank you, girl.
謝謝，閨女
What's this?
這是什麼？
That's a Mockingjay.
這是「自由夢幻」
How much?
多少錢？
- You keep it. It's yours. - Thank you.
- 拿著吧，歸你了 - 謝謝
Mom.
媽媽
Look at you!
看看你！
You look beautiful.
真漂亮
But you better tuck in that tail,little duck.
但最好把這個掖在後面，小鴨子
I laid something out for you, too.
我也給你準備了點東西
Okay.
好的
Now you look beautiful, too.
現在你也很漂亮了
Wish I looked like you.
真希望我能像你一樣
No. l wish I looked like you, little duck.
不，我希望像你一樣漂亮，小鴨子
Hey. You want to see what I got you today?
嘿，想看看今天我給你帶什麼了嗎？
It's a Mockingjay pin. To protect you.
這是自由夢幻胸針，可以保護你
And as long as you have it, nothing bad will happen to you.
只要你戴著它，就不會有霉運
Okay? I promise.
好麼？我保證
Prim, it's okay. It's okay.
普利姆，沒事的
Okay. It's time to sign in now. Okay?
現在開始登記了，好嗎？
They're gonna prick your finger just to take a little bit of blood.
他們會戳一下你的手指取一點點血
- You didn't say... - I know.
- 你之前不是說… - 我知道
It doesn't hurt much. Just a little.
並不會很痛，一點點而已
Okay? Go sit down there with the little kids. I'll find you after. Okay?
好麼？登記完去和那些小朋友坐一起 然後我會去找你，明白麼？
Next.
下一個
Go ahead. Next.
繼續，下一個
It's okay.
沒事的
Welcome! Welcome, welcome.
歡迎！歡迎，歡迎
Happy Hunger Games.
飢餓遊戲快樂
And may the odds be ever in your favor.
希望好運永遠站在你這邊
Now, before we begin, we have a very special film.
現在，開始之前，我們有一部特別的影片
Brought to you all the way from The Capitol.
為了大家從凱匹特一路帶回來的
War. Terrible war.
戰爭，可怕的戰爭
War.
戰爭
Terrible war. Widows, orphans, a motherless child.
可怕的戰爭，寡婦、孤兒和失去母親的孩子
This was the uprising that rocked our land.
暴動使我們的國家陷入內亂
Thirteen districts rebelled against the country that fed them,
13區背叛了一直哺育、熱愛
loved them, protected them.
和保護他們的祖國
Brother turned on brother until nothing remained.
同胞之前互相殘殺直至所剩無幾
And then came the peace, hard fought, sorely won.
之後便迎來和平，這是一次艱難的戰鬥，慘痛的勝利
A people rose up from the ashes, and a new era was born.
人們浩劫餘生，一個新紀元誕生了
But freedom has a cost. And the traitors were defeated.
但自由是需要付出代價的，叛徒被擊敗了
We swore as a nation we would never know this treason again.
做為國民我們發誓永遠不會讓悲劇重演
And so it was decreed that each year the various districts of Panem
所以法律規定施惠國的不同區域每年
would offer up, in tribute, one young man and woman
要奉上一對少年男女作為貢品
to fight to the death in a pageant of honor, courage, and sacrifice.
為了榮譽、勇氣和奉獻戰鬥至死
The lone victor, bathed in riches, would serve as a reminder
唯一的倖存者會變得非常富有
of our generosity and our forgiveness.
以此彰顯我們的慷慨和寬恕
This is how we remember our past.
這就是我們銘記過往
This is how we safeguard our future.
保護未來的方式
I just love that!
我很喜歡這段話！
Now, the time has come for us to select
現在，是時候讓我們選擇
one courageous young man and woman
一對勇敢的年輕男女
for the honor of representing District 12 in the 74th Annual Hunger Games.
作為第74屆年度飢餓遊戲12區榮譽代表了
As usual, ladies first.
像往常一樣，女士優先
Primrose Everdeen.
普利姆羅斯·埃弗丁
Where are you, dear?
親愛的，你在哪？
Come on up.
上來吧
Well, come on up.
來吧
Prim! Prim!
普利姆！普利姆！
No. No!
不，不！
I volunteer! I volunteer!
我當志願者！我要當志願者！
I volunteer as Tribute!
我自願作為貢品！
I believe we have a volunteer, Mr. Mayor.
我們擁有一位志願者，市長先生
Prim, you need to get out of here. You need to get out of here.
普利姆，你得馬上離開這，快走
- No!No! - Go find Mom!
- 不！不！ - 去找媽媽！
- Prim, go find Mom right now. I'm so sorry. - No!
- 普利姆，現在去找媽媽，很抱歉 - 不！
- Go find Mom. Prim, leave! Go find Mom. - No!No!No!
- 去找媽媽，普利姆，快走！去找媽媽！ - 不！不！不！
- Come on.
不！不！不！
A dramatic turn of events here in District 12.
12區出現了戲劇性的轉變
Yes, well.
好了
District 12's very first volunteer. Bring her up.
12區史上第一位志願者 帶她上來
Come on, dear.
來，親愛的
What's your name?
你叫什麼名字？
Katniss Everdeen.
凱特尼斯·埃弗丁
Well, I bet my hat that was your sister, wasn't it?
我打賭她一定是你妹妹，對嗎？
Yes.
是的
Let's have a big hand for our very first volunteer, Katniss Everdeen.
讓我們對第一位志願者，凱特尼斯·埃弗丁，報以熱烈掌聲!
And now for the boys.
現在輪到男孩了
Peeta Mellark.
皮塔·麥拉克
Here we are.
人齊了
Our Tributes from District 12.
這就是我們12區的貢品
Well, go on, you two, shake hands.
好了，你們倆握個手吧
Happy Hunger Games.
飢餓遊戲快樂
And may the odds be ever in your favor.
希望好運永遠站在你這邊
You have three minutes.
給你三分鐘
It's okay.
沒事的
Prim. Prim. It's okay. Prim, I don't have much time.
普利姆，普利姆，沒事 普利姆，我沒多少時間了
Prim. Listen. You're gonna be okay. Don't take any extra food from them.
普利姆，聽著，你會沒事的 不要從他們那拿走額外的食物
It isn't worth putting your name in more times. Okay?
這不值得多次記錄你的名字，好嗎？
Listen, Prim. Gale will bring you game. You can sell cheese from your goat.
聽著，普利姆，蓋爾會帶你玩的 你可以把羊奶酪賣掉
Just try to win. Maybe you can.
要努力贏得比賽，也許你可以的
Of course.
當然
And maybe I can. I am smart, you know?
或許我能贏的，我很聰明，知道麼？
- And you can hunt. - Exactly.
- 你會打獵 - 對呀
To protect you.
保護你
Thank you.
謝謝
You can't tune out again.
你不能再被選為貢品了
- I won't. - No, you can't. Not like when Dad died.
- 不會的 - 不，你不能。別像爸爸死的時候一樣
I won't be there anymore. You're all she has.
我不能再到那了，你就是她的一切
No matter what you feel, you have to be there for her. Do you understand?
無論你是怎麼想的，你必須為了她去那，明白嗎？
Don't cry.
別哭
Don't cry. Don't. Don't.
別哭，別哭，別
- It's time. - Prim, it's okay.
- 時間到了 - 普利姆，沒事的
- Prim, it's okay. It's okay, Prim. - No!No!No!
- 普利姆，別擔心，沒事，普利姆 - 不！不！不！
I promise, Prim.
我保證，普利姆
- I'm fine. - Yeah, I know.
- 我很好 - 我知道
I am.
真沒事
Listen to me. You're stronger than they are. You are.
聽我說，你比他們任何一個人都優秀
- Get to a bow. - They may not have...
- 弄一個弓 - 他們可能沒有…
They will if you show them how good you are.
如果你足夠優秀他們會想辦法的
They just want a good show. That's all they want.
人們只是想要一場好看的比賽 僅此而已
If they don't have a bow, then you make one, okay?
如果他們沒有弓，你就做一個，好麼？
You know how to hunt.
你知道如何狩獵
Animals.
動物
It's no different, Katniss.
這沒什麼不同，凱特尼斯
There's 24 of us, Gale. Only one comes out.
我們有24個人，蓋爾，只有一個人能活著
Yeah. And it's gonna be you.
這個人一定是你
Okay.
好了
Take care of them, Gale. Whatever you do, don't let them starve.
照顧好她們，蓋爾 無論怎樣，別讓他們挨餓
- Let's go. - I'll see you soon, okay?
- 走吧 - 我會盡快再見到你的，好嗎？
You two are in for a treat.
你們倆會喜歡的
Crystal chandeliers, platinum doorknobs, and it flies.
水晶吊燈，白金門把手，速度快極了
We'll be at The Capitol in less than two days.
我們會在凱匹特停留不到兩天
Now, before you do anything else...
現在，在你做其他事之前…
200 miles per hour, and you can barely feel a thing.
200英里每小時，幾乎沒什麼感覺
I think it's one of the wonderful things about this opportunity,
即使你們在這，哪怕只有一小會
that even though you're here and even though it's just for a little while,
我想這次機遇也是一件很美妙的事情
you get to enjoy all of this.
你們可以享受這裏的一切
I'm going to find Haymitch. He's probably in the bar car.
我去找黑密斯，他可能在酒吧車廂那
Have you ever met him?
你之前見過他嗎？
Haymitch?
黑密斯？
You know, Katniss, he is our mentor. He did win this thing once.
你知道的，凱特尼斯，他是我們的導師，贏過一次比賽
Look, you know, if you don't want to talk, I understand,
好吧，如果你不想和我交談，我理解
but I just don't think there's anything wrong with getting a little bit of help.
但我不認為想得到一點幫助有什麼錯的
Congratulations.
恭喜
Where's the ice?
冰塊呢？
I don't know.
不知道
May I?
可以坐下嗎？
Okay, so... So when do we start?
好的，我們什麼時候開始？
So eager.
太心切了
Most of you aren't in such a hurry.
多數人都沒這麼猴急
Yeah. I wanna know what the plan is. You're our mentor.
我想知道計劃是什麼，你是我倆的導師啊
- You're supposed to go... - Mentor?
- 你應該… - 導師？
Yeah, our mentor.
是啊，我們的導師
You're supposed to tell us how to get sponsors and give us advice.
你應該告訴我們如何獲得贊助並給些建議
Okay.
好吧
Embrace the probability of your imminent death.
做好有可能將死的準備
And know, in your heart, that there's nothing I can do to save you.
要知道，在你們心中，我救不了你們
So why are you here then?
那你為什麼還在這？
The refreshments.
不愁吃喝
Okay, I think that's enough of that.
好吧，夠了
You made me spill my drink. These are brand new pants.
你把我的酒碰灑了，這可是條新褲子
You know, I think I'll go finish this in my room.
你懂的，等我回屋會把它喝完的
He's gonna come around.
他快醒酒了
It's no use.
沒用的
I'm gonna go talk to him.
我去和他談談
We have two very fit 16-year-olds.
我們有兩位非常合適的16歲隊員
Of course, of course. They always provide pretty good opponents.
當然，他們總是能夠提供優秀的競爭對手
Yes, yes, they do.
是啊
- Do you remember this year? - Of course.
- 還記得這一年嗎？ - 當然
One of my favorite years. And one of my favorite Arenas.
我最喜歡的比賽之一，阿瑞納斯表現很棒
The use of the rubble in the ruined city...
利用荒廢城市裏的碎石
Very exciting.
真令人興奮
And this moment here,
這個時刻
this moment is a moment that you never forget.
你永遠不會忘記
Yes.
是的
The moment when a Tribute becomes a victor.
當貢品變成勝利者的時刻
- You'd freeze to death first. - No, because I'd light a fire.
- 首先，你會被凍死 - 不會的，我可以點火
That's a good way to get killed.
是個找死的好辦法
What's a good way to get killed?
什麼找死的好辦法？
Joy. Why don't you join us?
有意思，怎麼不過來和我們一起聊聊？
I was just giving some life-saving advice.
我只是給些生存建議
Like what?
比如說？
I was just asking about how to find shelter.
我剛才問他如何找到避難所
Which would come in handy if, in fact, you were still alive.
這些遲早有用，實際上你們還活著
How do you find shelter?
你怎麼找到避難所的？
Pass the jam.
果醬給我
Give me a chance to wake up , sweetheart.
寶貝，讓我喘口氣吧
This mentoring is very taxing stuff.
作為導師，這活可不輕鬆
Can you pass the marmalade?
能把果醬遞給我嗎？
That is mahogany!
那可是紅木！
Look at you. Just killed a placemat.
看看你，對餐具墊發什麼火
You really want to know how to stay alive?
你真想知道如何才能生存下來嗎？
You get people to like you.
你得讓觀眾喜歡你
Not what you were expecting?
並不是你所期望的那樣
Well, when you're in the middle of The Games and you're starving or freezing,
當你處於遊戲當中，你會挨餓挨凍
some water, a knife, or even some matches
水、刀子，甚至是火柴
can mean the difference between life and death.
都關乎你的生死
And those things only come from sponsors.
這些東西取決於贊助商
And to get sponsors, you have to make people like you.
想獲得贊助商的青睞，你必須讓觀眾喜歡你
And right now, sweetheart, you're not off to a real good start.
寶貝，現在你離一個好的開頭並不遠了
There it is.
就是那
It's huge!
真壯觀！
That's incredible.
不可思議
Peeta, I love you.
皮塔，我愛你
Come on. Come on.
來，來啊
You better keep this knife. He knows what he's doing.
你最好留著這把刀，他清楚自己在做什麼
So now that you've seen them,
現在你已經看到他們了
what do you think about this year's crop of recruits?
你認為今年的新選手怎麼樣？
Are there any surprises that we can expect this year?
有什麼值得期待的亮點嗎？
It's really hard to tell just from a Reaping,
僅從抽籤來看真的很難說
-but I think this is a very interesting mix. - Yes.
- 但我認為這將是一場非常有趣的混戰 - 沒錯
And whenever you have a volunteer from an outlying district,
而且這次還有一位邊遠區域的志願者
that's something you can't ignore.
這絕對是個看點
What's that?
那是什麼？
We're just saying we might need to hose you down again
我們只是在談論在你見西納之前
before we take you to Cinna.
可能需要再幫你沖洗一遍
That was one of the bravest things I've ever seen. With your sister?
替妹妹作為貢品，這是我見過的最勇敢的行為
- My name's Cinna. - Katniss.
- 我叫西納 - 凱特尼斯
I'm sorry that this happened to you,
對於你的遭遇感到很抱歉
and I'm here to help you in any way that I can.
我會盡我所能幫助你
Most people just congratulate me.
多數人只是恭喜我罷了
Well, I don't see the point in that.
我不會那麼想
So tonight, they have the Tribute Parade.
今晚有貢品巡遊活動
I'm gonna take you out and show you off to the world.
我要讓全世界看到你有多漂亮
So you're here to make me look pretty?
你在這就是為了打扮我？
I'm here to help you make an impression.
我是為了讓觀眾對有個好印象
Now, usually they dress people in the clothes from their district.
通常他們根據貢品所在區域特點來打扮
- Yeah, we're always coalminers. - Yeah, but I don't wanna do that.
- 好啊，我們那全是礦工 - 我不會那麼幹的
I wanna do something that they're gonna remember.
我要做的一定會令他們難忘
Did they explain about trying to get sponsors?
他們跟你說過如何才能獲得贊助商嗎？
Yeah, but I'm not very good at making friends.
說了，但我並不擅長交朋友
We'll see.
走著瞧吧
I just think somebody that brave
我想有膽量的人
shouldn't be dressed up in some stupid costume, now should they?
不應該穿得太隨便，對嗎？
I hope not.
希望如此
Okay, this is safe. I promise.
我保證這很安全
It's not real fire. These suits are built so you won't feel a thing.
這不是真正的火焰，衣服是量身定做的 不會感到任何不適
Looks pretty real to me.
看起來真的很合身
Well, that's the idea.
就是這意思
You ready?
準備好了嗎？
- Don't be afraid. - I'm not afraid.
- 別害怕 - 我不怕
Over 100,000 people craning to get a glimpse of this year's Tributes.
超過10萬人正迫不及待的等著觀賞今年的貢品
And the sponsors get to see the Tributes for the first time.
贊助商們也是第一次看到這些貢品
The importance of this moment cannot be overstated.
此刻的重要性無需贅言
Very nice.
很好
First chariot on my count, in 15, 14, 13...
第一輛戰車入場倒計時開始，15,14，13…
There they are. There they are. This year's Tributes.
來了，他們來啦，今年的貢品們
It's the most exciting part.
真令人激動
It just gives you goose bumps.
雞皮疙瘩都起來了
And don't you love how the stylists,
太喜歡這些設計師了
they so clearly are able to reflect the character of each district?
他們是怎麼把每個區域選手的特色 如此清晰呈現出來的？
- Right. Right. There's District 4. - Yes.
- 沒錯，第4區的選手來了 - 是啊
- Fishing. - I get it.
- 魚類裝扮 - 我看見了
- I like it. - That's very good.
- 我喜歡 - 很不錯
And behind them, we have two power plant workers. Right?
在他們後面有兩位電廠工人，對嗎？
And then...
然後呢…
What is that in the background?
最後那個是什麼？
Come on. They'll love it.
來吧，他們喜歡這樣。
Yeah!
耶！
Now see that? I love that.
看到了嗎？我喜歡
Two young people holding their hands up, saying,
兩個年輕人高舉緊握在一起的雙手
"I'm proud I come from District 12. We will not be overlooked."
喊著「我為來自12區感到自豪，我們不會被忽視的」
- Nope. - I love that!
- 當然不會 - 真棒我喜歡
People are sure gonna be paying attention to them right now.
所有人的注意力都集中在他們身上
And we're ready.
準備好了
President Snow, you're live.
斯諾總統，該你了
Welcome.
歡迎
Tributes, we welcome you.
貢品們，歡迎你們的到來！
We salute your courage and your sacrifice.
對於你們的勇氣和奉獻精神我們深表敬意
And we wish you
祝願你們
Happy Hunger Games.
飢餓遊戲快樂
And may the odds be ever in your favor.
希望好運永遠站在你這邊
That was amazing.
簡直難以置信
We are all anybody's going to be talking about.
所有人都在討論你們
So brave.
真夠大膽的
Are you sure you should be near an open flame?
你確信自己呆在我這團烈火旁會沒事嗎？
Fake flame? Are you sure you...
火焰道具嗎？你確信…
Let's go upstairs.
咱們上樓吧
So, each of the districts get their own floor.
每個區域都有屬於自己的樓層
And because you're from 12, you get the penthouse.
因為你們來自12區，所以閣樓是你們的
Come on.
來
So this is the living room.
這是客廳
I know, I know.
我知道
Now, your rooms are right over here.
你們的臥室在這
Why don't you go clean yourselves up a little before dinner?
在晚餐開始之前為什麼不先去洗個澡呢？
In two weeks, 23 of you will be dead.
兩周內，會有23個人死掉
One of you will be alive.
只有一個倖存者
Who that is depends on how well you pay attention over the next four days,
這取決於你們是否在意接下來的四天
particularly to what I'm about to say.
尤其是我將要說的這些事
First, no fighting with the other Tributes.
首先，不要和其它選手打鬥
You'll have plenty of time for that in the Arena.
在競技場你們有的是時間
There are four compulsory exercises. The rest will be individual training.
有四個必修練習，其餘的是個人訓練
My advice is don't ignore the survival skills.
我建議你們不要忽視生存技能
Everybody wants to grab a sword,
每個人都想奪取利劍
but most of you will die from natural causes.
但多數人都會死於自然因素
10% from infection, 20% from dehydration.
10%的人死於感染，20%的人死於脫水
Exposure can kill as easily as a knife.
暴曬能像刀子一樣輕易致人死地
- Jason, where's my knife, huh? - I didn't touch your knife.
- 傑森，我的刀呢？ - 我沒碰你的刀
- I put my knife right there! - Don't touch me. I didn't touch your knife!
- 我就把刀放那了！ - 別碰我，我沒拿你的刀！
- Yes, you took my knife! - I didn't touch your knife!
- 你拿了！ - 我沒拿！
- You took my knife, you liar! - I didn't touch your knife.
- 你拿我的刀了，騙子！ - 我沒拿
- You liar! - I didn't touch your knife!
- 騙子！ - 我沒拿！
You little punk! He took my knife!
臭小子！他拿我刀！
- Get off me! - I'm just sitting here.
- 放開我！ - 我一直坐在這
I'll finish you right now, kid!
我現在就把我幹掉，臭小子！
Actually, better yet, I'll wait for the Arena.
好啊，我在競技場等你
You're the first one I get, so watch your back.
我第一個就去收拾你，給我小心點
- Everybody, back in line! - You know who you're messing with, kid!
- 大家退後！ - 你知道你得罪誰了，臭小子！
He's a Career. You know what that is?
他是職業幹這個的，知道什麼意思嗎？
- From District 1. - And 2.
- 從第1區來的 - 還有第2區
They train in a special academy until they're 18. Then they volunteer.
他們18歲前都在專門的培訓機構訓練 然後作為志願者參賽
By that point, they're pretty lethal.
這也就意味著他們很難對付
But they don't receive any special treatment.
但他們沒有任何特殊待遇
In fact, they stay in the exact same apartment as you do.
實際上，他們和你們呆在相同的房間內
And I don't think they let them have dessert. And you can.
他們沒有餐後甜點可以吃，而你們卻有
So how good are they?
他們實力有多強？
Obviously they're pretty good. They win it almost every year, but...
顯然他們很優秀，差不多每年都會獲勝，但…
Almost.
差不多
...they can be arrogant.
他們太自大了
And arrogance can be a big problem.
自大是個嚴重問題
I hear you can shoot.
聽說你會射箭
I'm all right.
還好吧
No, she's better than all right. My father buys her squirrels.
她射箭技術很好的，我爸買過她的松鼠
He says she hits them right in the eye every time.
他說她每次都是箭無虛發
- Peeta's strong. - What?
- 皮塔很強壯 - 什麼？
He can throw a 100-pound sack of flour right over his head. I've seen it.
他可以把100磅的麵粉舉過頭頂，我見過
Okay, well, I'm not gonna kill anybody with a sack of flour.
好吧，我可不會用一袋麵粉殺人
No, but you might have a better chance of winning
但你可以用更好的方式獲勝
if somebody comes after you with a knife.
如果有人拿刀過來
I have no chance of winning! None! All right?
我贏不了！贏不了！懂嗎？
It's true. Everybody knows it.
這是真的，大家都知道
You know what my mother said?
你知道我媽怎麼說的嗎？
She said District 12 might finally have a winner.
他說12區可能會有一個勝者
But she wasn't talking about me.
但她說的不是我
She was talking about you.
是你
I'm not very hungry.
我不太餓
I'm done, too.
我也吃完了
Throw that metal thing over there.
把那個金屬東西扔過去
What?
什麼？
No. Haymitch said we're not supposed to show our skills.
不，黑密斯說過不讓我們展露自己的才能
I don't care what Haymitch said.
我不管黑密斯怎麼說的
Those guys are looking at you like you're a meal.
那幾個傢伙視你為砧板魚肉
Throw it.
扔過去
Hi.
嗨
How did you do that?
你怎麼做到的？
I used to decorate the cakes down at the bakery.
我過去經常在麵包店做蛋糕美化工作
I'll show you.
給你看看
See?
看到了嗎？
Yeah.
看到了
Hey, I think you have a shadow.
有人跟著你
Tomorrow, they'll bring you in one by one and evaluate you.
明天他們會把你們一個接一個的帶進去 並且評估你們的能力
This is important, because higher ratings will mean sponsors.
這點很重要，因為打分較高的意味著會有更多的贊助
This is the time to show them everything.
是時候嶄露頭角了
There'll be a bow. Make sure you use it.
在那會有個弓，你一定要好好利用
Peeta, you make sure to show your strength.
皮塔，你也一定要展示出你的力量
They'll start with District 1, so the two of you will go last.
他們會從第1區開始，所以你們會排在最後
I don't know how else to put this. Make sure they remember you.
不知道該怎麼說，總之一定要讓他們記住你們
Katniss Everdeen.
凱特尼斯·埃弗丁
Hey, Katniss?
嘿，凱特尼斯？
Shoot straight.
好好表現
Katniss Everdeen.
凱特尼斯·埃弗丁
District 12.
12區的
Hey, hey, hey-
嘿，嘿，嘿
Hey, who ordered this pig? Who ordered this pig? Hey!
嘿，誰點的乳豬？誰點的乳豬？嘿！
Did you get some pig yet?
你吃過乳豬沒？
Thank you for your consideration.
謝謝，僅供您參考
- Are you crazy? - I just got mad.
- 你瘋了嗎？ - 我太生氣了
Mad?
生氣？
You realize that your actions reflect badly on all of us. Notjust you.
你得意識到你的不良舉動會影響整個團隊 不只是你自己
They just want a good show. It's fine.
他們只是想要一場好看的比賽，沒事的
How about it's just bad manners, Cinna! How about that?
這麼沒禮貌你覺得會怎麼樣，西納！ 會怎麼樣？
Well, finally! I hope you noticed we have a serious situation.
好吧，我希望你注意到我們的形勢很嚴峻
Nice shooting, sweetheart.
幹得漂亮，寶貝
What did they do when you shot the apple?
當你射中蘋果時他們什麼反應？
Well, they looked pretty startled.
他們都驚呆了
Yeah.
耶
Now, what did you say? "Thanks for..."
你說什麼來著？「謝謝…」
- Thanks for your consideration. -"...your consideration."
- 謝謝，僅供您參考 - 「…供您參考」
Genius! Genius.
天才！天才！
I don't think we're gonna find this funny if the Gamemakers decide to take it out...
如果遊戲製作者想把我們踢出局的話 我想就沒這麼好笑了
On who? On her?
踢誰？她？
On him?
還是他？
I think they already have. Loosen your corset, have a drink.
我認為他們已經具備參賽資格了 放輕鬆，喝一杯
I would have given anything to see it.
我原本會不惜一切代價看到結果的
As you know, the Tributes were rated on a scale of 1 to 12
正如你們所知道的，經過三天的仔細評估
after three days of careful evaluation.
1至12區的貢品評分結果出來了
The Gamekeepers would like to acknowledge that it was an exceptional...
遊戲管理人得知了一個非常意外的…
From District 1, Marvel, with a score of nine.
來自第1區的，漫威，9分
From District 2, Cato, with a score of 10.
來自第2區的，卡托，10分
Clove, with a score of 10.
克勞芙，10分
From District 3... From District 4, with a score of...
來自第3區的… 來自第4區的…
From District 7...
來自第7區的
From District 8...
來自第8區的…
And Rue with a score of seven.
茹，7分
Now our final district.
最後一個區了
From District 12. Peeta Mellark.
來自第12區的，皮塔·麥拉克
A score of eight.
8分
- Excellent. - Peeta!
- 棒極了 - 皮塔！
Bravo.
精彩
- We can work with that. - Good job.
- 我們能做到的 - 幹得好
And finally,
最後一位
from District 12,
來自第12區的
Katniss E verdeen.
凱特尼斯·埃弗丁
With a score of...
分數是…
Eleven.
11分！
- Katniss! - Outstanding!
- 凱特尼斯！ - 難以置信！
- Yes! - Eleven?
- 太好了！ - 11分？
Congratulations.
恭喜你
I thought they hated me.
我以為他們恨死我了
They must have liked your guts.
他們喜歡你的勇氣
To Katniss Everdeen, The Girl on Fire!
敬凱特尼斯·埃弗丁，燃燒女孩！
Goodness. We are.
天吶
An 11?
有個11分？
She earned it.
她應得的
She shot an arrow at your head.
她把箭射在你腦袋上
Well, at an apple.
是蘋果上
Near your head.
離你腦袋也不遠了
Sit down.
坐下
Seneca, why do you think we have a winner?
塞內卡，你想想為什麼我們要選出一名勝者？
What do you mean?
您的意思是？
I mean, why do we have a winner?
我的意思是為什麼要一個人活下來？
I mean, if we just wanted to intimidate the districts,
如果我們只是威脅其它的區域
why not round up 24 of them at random and execute them all at once?
為什麼不隨機選24個人組到一起讓他們立刻比賽呢？
Be a lot faster.
這樣多塊
Hope.
希望
Hope?
希望什麼？
It is the only thing stronger than fear.
這是唯一強於恐懼的
A little hope is effective. A lot of hope is dangerous.
一點希望可以讓人絕處逢生 希望太大的話是很危險的
A spark is fine, as long as it's contained.
火花可以有，但一定得能控制住
So...
所以…
So contain it.
讓一切都在可掌控的範圍內
Right.
好的
So she's staring at all my jewels. She cannot take her eyes off of them.
她目不轉睛的盯著我身上的珠寶
- Well, look at all that that you're wearing. - Frankly, it was rude.
- 是啊，從上到下打量一遍 - 說真的，這太無禮了
Haymitch, you should join us.
黑密斯，一起來吧
We're having some of your favorite for dinner.
晚餐有你的最愛
Lovely.
那太好了
- Where's Peeta? - He's in his room.
- 皮塔呢？ - 他在房間裏
Now, listen, tomorrow's the last day.
聽著，明天是最後一天
And they let us work with our own Tributes right before The Games,
比賽前他們讓我們和自己的隊員呆在一起
so you and I will be going down at 9:00.
所以咱倆9點前得呆在一起
What about him?
他呢？
He says he wants to be trained on his own from now on.
他說從現在開始想一個人訓練
What?
什麼？
This kind of thing does happen at this point. There's only one winner, right?
這個時候還說這種事，贏家只有一個，別忘了
We should have some chocolate-covered strawberries.
巧克力草莓還沒上來呢
- Oh, my, yes. - Please.
- 噢，我喜歡吃 - 能不能行了
Ladies and gentlemen, your master of ceremonies,
女士們，先生們，歡迎我們的節目主持人
Caesar Flickerman!
凱撒·弗裏克曼
Thank you! Thank you!
謝謝大家！謝謝！
Welcome, welcome, welcome to the 74th Annual Hunger Games!
歡迎，歡迎觀看第74屆年度飢餓遊戲大賽！
Now, in about five minutes, they're all going to be out here.
大約5分鐘後，他們所有人都將到舞台上來
All of the Tributes that you've heard about.
所有你們瞭解的選手們齊聚一堂
Are you excited?
激動嗎？
Let me hear it!
我聽不見！
Amazing.
太棒了
I don't feel amazing.
我並不覺得怎麼樣
Don't you know how beautiful you look?
難道你不覺得自己很漂亮嗎？
No. And I don't know how to make people like me.
不覺得，我也不知道怎麼才能讓別人喜歡上我
- How do you make people like you? - Well, you made me like you.
- 你怎麼討別人喜歡的？ - 你已經讓我喜歡上你了
That's different. I wasn't trying.
這不一樣，我還不夠好
Exactly. Just be yourself, I'll be there the whole time.
就是這樣，做自己就行，我會一直在那
And just pretend that you're talking to me. Okay?
你只要假裝和我說話就行，好嗎？
Okay.
好吧
Let's see if she does indeed shine.
讓我們瞧瞧她是否真的光芒閃耀
Let's have a warm round of applause for Glimmer!
掌聲歡迎格裏姆！
Glimmer, are you prepared?
格裏姆，準備好了嗎？
Yes, Caesar, I am very prepared.
當然，凱撒，早就準備好了
I like it. That's assurance. That's self-assurance.
我喜歡，你很自信
- Don't you think? - And, as you can see...
- 難道你不覺得嗎？ - 就像你看到的一樣…
...I'm wearing one of our own creations.
我穿的是我們自己設計的服裝
A big round of applause!
請報以熱烈掌聲！
Marvel!
漫威！
Welcome, Clove.
歡迎，克勞芙
- It's an honor representing my district. - You're a fighter.
- 很榮幸代表我的區域參賽 - 你是個鬥士
I'm prepared. I'm vicious. I'm ready to go.
我準備好了，我可不友善，隨時出發
Cato!
卡托！
I find that if I can apply myself to the situation present,
我發現如果自己能夠接受現在的情況
I will be able to figure it out.
我一定會有辦法獲勝的
Thank you. Lovely to see you. Thank you so much.
謝謝，很高興見到你 非常感謝
Good. So you can climb trees.
你會爬樹
You're pretty quick. And are you a hunter?
動作很敏捷，你是獵人麼？
A gatherer?
還是收集果實的？
From District 12, District 12...
從第12區來的，第12區…
You know her as The Girl on Fire!
被大家所熟知的燃燒女孩！
Well, we know her as the lovely Katniss Everdeen!
我們稱她為可愛的凱特尼斯·埃弗丁
Welcome! Welcome.
歡迎！歡迎！
Welcome.
歡迎！
Well, that was quite an entrance you made the other day.
那天你的入場很特別
What?
你說什麼？
I think someone's a little nervous.
我想某人有點緊張
I said that was quite an entrance that you made
我是說在不久前貢品巡遊那天
at the Tribute Parade the other day.
你的入場方式很特別
Do you want to tell us about it?
想和我們談談這個嗎？
Well, I was just hoping that I wouldn't burn to death.
好，我只是希望別被燒死了
When you came out of that chariot,
當你從戰車上下來的時候
I have to say, my heart stopped.
不得不說，我的心臟都停止跳動了
Did any of you experience this as well?
你們也有類似的感覺吧？
My heart stopped.
心跳停止了
So did mine.
我也一樣
Now, tell me about the flames. Are they real?
和我說說那火焰吧，是真的嗎？
Yes.
是的
In fact, I'm wearing them today. Would you like to see?
事實上今天我也帶來了，你們想看嗎？
Wait, wait, wait. Is it safe?
等一下，這安全嗎？
Yes.
當然
What do you think, folks?
觀眾們，你們是怎麼想的？
I think that's a yes.
我想一定會同意
Steady. Steady.
淡定，淡定
Lovely. Thank you.
太好看了，謝謝
That was really something. Katniss, that was something.
真了不起，凱特尼斯，太了不起了
That was something. Thank you for that.
了不起，謝謝你的表演
I have one more question for you.
還有一個問題
It's about your sister.
關於你的妹妹
We were all very moved, I think, when you volunteered for her at the Reaping.
當你在抽籤日那天作為自願者替她參賽的時候 我們都很感動
Did she come and say goodbye to you?
她和你告別了嗎？
Yes.
是的
- She did.
- 告別了 - 好的
And what did you say to her in the end?
最後你跟她說什麼了？
I told her that I would try to win.
我告訴她會盡全力贏得比賽
That I would try to win for her.
為了她
Of course you did.
當然
And try you will.
你會盡力的
Ladies and gentlemen, from District 12,
女士們，先生們，來自第12區的
Katniss Everdeen, The Girl on Fire!
凱特尼斯·埃弗丁，燃燒女孩！
You did it, darling. That was incredible.
你做到了，親愛的，不可思議
Thank you.
謝謝
Nice job, sweetheart.
幹得漂亮，寶貝
Nice dress, too.
衣服不錯
- Not yours. - Please welcome Peeta Mellark!
- 沒說你 - 請大家歡迎皮塔·莫拉克
Peeta, welcome.
皮塔，歡迎
How are you finding The Capitol? And don't say, "With a map. "
你怎麼找到凱匹特的？別跟我說「看地圖找的」
It's different. It's very different than back home.
當然不是，這裏和家不一樣
Different. In what way? Give us an example.
不一樣，你指哪方面？舉個例子
Okay. Well, the showers here are weird.
好的，淋浴感覺挺古怪的
- The showers? - Yes.
- 淋浴？ - 是的
We have different showers.
咱們的淋浴不一樣
I have a question for you, Caesar. Do I smell like roses to you?
有個問題想問你，凱撒 你聞我身上有玫瑰的味道嘛？
- Take a whiff? - All right.
- 再近一點 - 好
- You see? - Yes. Do I smell like it?
- 聞到了嗎？ - 嗯，我聞起來有玫瑰的味道嘛？
- You definitely smell better than I do. - Well, I've lived here longer.
- 你的聞起來一定比我強 - 那是，我在這呆的比你久
That makes sense.
有道理
Very funny. So, Peeta, tell me,
真有趣，皮塔，和我說說
is there a special girl back home?
在家有沒有對你來講意義特殊的女孩子？
No. No. Not really.
沒，沒有，算不上
No? I don't believe it for a second. Look at that face.
沒有？我一點也不信，看看這張臉
Handsome man like you. Peeta, tell me.
像你這麼帥的小伙子，皮塔，招了吧
Well, there...
額，有…
There is this one girl that I've had a crush on forever.
我一直迷戀著一個女孩
But I don't think she actually recognized me until the Reaping.
但實際上我並不認為她能認識我，直到抽籤日那天
Well, I'll tell you what, Peeta.
我來告訴你吧，皮塔
You go out there and you win this thing,
從競技場走出去你就會贏得想要的東西
and when you get home, she'll have to go out with you.
當你回家的時候，他一定會和你在一起的
Right, folks?
對嗎？朋友們
Thanks, but I don't think winning's gonna help me at all.
謝謝，但我並不覺得獲勝能幫什麼忙
And why not?
怎麼呢？
Because she came here with me.
因為她和我都在這
Well, that's bad luck.
真不走運
Yeah, it is.
的確是這樣
- And I wish you all the best of luck. - Thank you.
- 祝你一切順利 - 謝謝
Peeta Mellark.
皮塔·莫拉克
District 12!
來自第12區！
What the hell was that?
剛才是怎麼回事？
You don't talk to me, and then you say you have a crush on me?
之前你不和我說話，現在你又說喜歡我？
You say you want to train alone? Is that how you want to play?
你說你想獨立訓練，這是你想做的嗎？
Stop it! Stop it!
住手！住手！
- Let's start right now! - Hey!
- 咱倆把話說清楚！ - 嘿！
- He did you a favor. - He made me look weak.
- 他在幫你 - 他讓我看起來很脆弱
He made you look desirable, which in your case, can't hurt, sweetheart.
他使你看起來令人滿意 像你這種情況，不能傷心，寶貝
He's right, Katniss.
他說的對，凱特尼斯
Of course I'm right.
當然沒錯
Now, I can sell the star-crossed lovers from District 12...
我可以出賣你們這對倒霉情侶
We are not star-crossed lovers.
我倆不是情侶
It's a television show!
這是電視節目！
And being in love with that boy might just get you sponsors,
和他相愛也許會得到贊助商的青睞
which could save your damn life.
這樣才能讓你們保命
Okay. Why don't you get out of here?
好吧，你還在這幹什麼？
Maybe I can deliver you both in one piece tomorrow.
也許明天我能拯救你們兩個
Manners!
禮貌點！
You, too?
你也沒睡？
Hey.
嘿
Can't sleep?
睡不著嗎？
No. Of course not.
是啊，睡不著。
I'm sorry I went after you.
對於你的追求我很抱歉
You know, I meant that as a compliment.
你知道的，那只是在恭維你
I know.
我懂
Listen to them.
聽他們的話吧
Yeah.
嗯
I just don't want them to change me.
我只是不想讓他們改變我
How would they change you?
他們怎麼改變你了？
I don't know. They'd turn me into something I'm not.
不知道，他們使我變得有點不像我了
I just don't want to be another piece in their game, you know?
我只是不想在遊戲里變成另外一個人，你懂嗎？
You mean you won't kill anyone?
你的意思是不殺任何人？
No.
不
I mean, I'm sure I would, just like anybody else
我是說我確定不會殺人的，和其他人一樣
when the time came,
當比賽開始時
but I just keep wishing that I could think of a way to show them
我仍希望可以通過一種方式來向他們傳達
that they don't own me.
我並不屬於他們
If I'm gonna die, I want to still be me.
即使我要死了，我也要做我自己
Does that make any sense?
你覺得有道理嗎？
Yeah.
是啊
I just can't afford to think like that.
只是我還沒想過這些
I have my sister.
我還有妹妹
Yeah, I know.
我知道
I guess I'll see you tomorrow.
咱們明天見吧
See you tomorrow.
明天見
They'll put all kinds of stuff right in front, right in the mouth of the Cornucopia.
他們會把所有物品放在豐饒角前面的開口處 （註：豐饒角，位於比賽起點的建築，四周放有生存物資。）
There'll even be a bow there. Don't go for it.
在那還有一把弓箭，你別去拿它
Why not?
為什麼不能拿？
It's a bloodbath. They're trying to pull you in.
遊戲剛開始會有一場大屠殺 你會被捲進去的
That's not your game.
這不是你一個人的遊戲
You turn, run, find high ground, look for water.
你要轉身快跑，找個高地，尋找水源
Water's your new best friend.
水是你最好的新朋友
Don't step off that pedestal early or they'll blow you sky high.
別提前走基座上走下來，他們會把你吹上天的
I won't.
我不會的
Katniss, you can do this.
凱特尼斯，你能做到的
Thanks.
謝謝
Give me your arm.
伸出手臂
- Give me your arm. - What is that?
- 伸出手臂 - 這是什麼？
Your tracker.
追蹤器
We're up.
準備就緒
All right. Less than a minute, people. Final checks.
好的，還有不到一分鐘，夥計們 最後檢查一遍
There are 15 out. They are flying.
還有15秒，準備起飛
Here.
這
Thank you.
謝謝
Thirty seconds.
30秒
I'm not allowed to bet, but if I could, I'd bet on you.
我被禁止賭博 如果我可以下個賭注的話，一定賭你贏
Twenty seconds.
20秒
Ten seconds.
10秒
Okay, they're in the tubes.
好的，他們進管道了
50, 49, 48, 47,
50, 49, 48, 47,
46, 45, 44, 43,
46, 45, 44, 43,
42, 41, 40,
42, 41, 40,
39, 38, 37, 36,
39, 38, 37, 36,
35, 34, 33, 32,
35, 34, 33, 32,
31, 30, 29, 28,
31, 30, 29, 28,
27, 26, 25,
27, 26, 25,
24, 23, 22...
24, 23, 22...
And, of course, there's the familiar "boom" of the cannon,
又是一次熟悉的噩耗
which marks the end of another fallen Tribute.
屏幕上標記的是挑戰失敗的貢品
Twenty-five? Got it.
25？收到
He's moving now.
他在移動
Well, that makes 13 gone in the first eight hours.
在第一個8小時內有13名選手挑戰失敗
And Claudius, I think I see an alliance forming.
克勞迪亞斯，我想我看到一個正在逐步形成聯盟
Wait! Did you see the look on her face?
等下！你看到她的表情了嗎？
- How stupid can you get? - A fire?
- 你怎麼知道她在那？ - 看到火光了嗎？
"Oh, no! Please don't kill me! Oh, no!"
「不！求求你，別殺我！不！」
That's actually a good impression.
真令人印象深刻
Hey, lover boy!
嘿，小白臉！
- You sure she went this way? - Yeah, I'm sure.
- 你確定她走的是這條路嗎？ - 我確定
You better be.
最好沒錯
Yeah, that was her snare we found back there.
那是她佈置的陷阱，我在那後面找到的
Are you sure we shouldn't just kill him now?
我們現在怎麼不把他幹掉呢？
Nah. He's our best chance of finding her.
算了，有他在我們才能找到那女孩
Let's go.
走吧
Sir?
先生？
She is almost at the edge.
她一直在競技場的邊緣徘徊
Two kilometers away from the nearest Tribute.
離她最近的貢品也有2公里遠
Let's turn her around.
咱們得讓她掉頭
Cueing another. On my count. One, two...
另一個準備，開始計時，1，2
She's heading towards the left flank.
她往左側去了
Okay. Can you give me a tree right there?
好的，能在那放棵樹嗎？
Sure. Cueing tree.
可以，準備放樹
She's almost there.
她在那
Lucia, get a cannon ready.
露西婭，準備加農炮
There she is! There she is!
在那！她在那！
- She's mine! - Not if I get her first!
- 她是我的！ - 先到先得！
- Where you gonna go? - Mine!
- 你往哪跑？ - 她是我的！
Fish out of the pond! And someone found her.
把池塘翻個遍，一定要找到她
- There she is! - Yeah!
- 她在那！ - 耶！
Here we go!
我們來啦！
- Where you going, huh? - Get her, Cato!
- 往哪跑？ - 抓住他，卡托！
Where do you think you're going?
你以為能跑哪去？
Where you going, baby?
往哪跑，寶貝
Three o'clock.
3點鐘方向
- Where you going, Girl on Fire? - We got her!
- 你去哪，燃燒女孩？ - 我們抓到她了！
Miss Everdeen, I'm gonna get you!
埃弗丁小姐，我會抓住你的！
That's not gonna help you up there, Katniss.
爬那麼高無濟於事的，凱特尼斯
Where are you going?
你想往哪去啊？
- Go get her, man! - You are so done.
- 去抓她！ - 你能行的
Just get her, Cato!
卡托，上！
- He's gonna get you, Katniss. - Look at her scurry.
- 他來抓你了，凱特尼斯 - 看把她急的
Right up there.
快逮到她了
- Kill her! - Just go, keep going!
- 殺了她！ - 繼續爬啊
- Go, Cato. - Come on, Cato.
加油，卡托
- She's right there. - Go, Cato! Come on, Cato!
- 她就在那了 - 卡托！加油！卡托！
You got this.
快到了
Go! He's got this.
爬啊！
- Kill her, Cato! Just get her, Cato! - Go! Go!
- 殺了她，卡托！抓住她，卡托！ - 上啊！
- Take her down!
- 把她弄下來！ - 快爬啊！
- You got this, Cato! - Come on, kill her!
- 就快到了，卡托！ - 加油，殺了她！
I'm coming for you!
我來取你小命了！
Come on, Cato!
加油，卡托！
I'll do it myself.
我自己來
Give me that before...
讓我來
- Get her. - Come on. Come on, come on!
- 把她射下來 - 加油，射啊！
Maybe you should throw the sword!
你們應該把刀扔上來試試！
Let's just wait her out.
我們等她下來吧
She's gotta come down at some point. It's that or starve to death.
過段時間她會下來的，否則就得餓死
We'll just kill her then.
然後我們再找她算賬
Okay.
好的
Somebody make a fire.
誰去生把火
- Let's make camp over here! - Hurry up with the fire.
- 我們就在這露營 - 快去生把火
Boys.
小孩子
[APPLY GENEROUSLY AND STAY ALIVE - H]
[把這些都敷在傷口上，活下去 - 黑密斯]
Thank you.
謝謝
Claudius, I think those are tracker jackers Am I wrong?
克勞迪亞斯，我想那些是殺人蜂，沒錯吧？
- Those things are very lethal. - Very.
- 它們相當有殺傷力 - 很致命
For those of you who don't know,
對於不瞭解的朋友，我再介紹一下
tracker jackers are genetically engineered wasps whose venom causes searing pain,
殺人蜂是經過基因改良過的黃蜂 毒液可以引起灼熱似的疼痛
powerful hallucinations, and in extreme cases, death.
強勁的幻覺，在極端情況下甚至可以導致死亡
Run!
跑！
Katniss, go!
凱特尼斯，快跑！
Get out of here! Go! What are you doing? Go!
離開這，快走！ 你在想什麼，快走！
Not only is it lethal, but the venom of a tracker jacker sting
不但極具殺傷力，而且只需一隻殺人蜂的毒液
can produce powerful hallucinations.
也能令人產生強勁的幻覺
Mom, don't just sit there and look at me! Please say something!
媽媽，別只是坐在那看我！ 說點什麼吧！
Katniss, go!
凱特尼斯，快跑！
Get out of here! Go! What are you doing? Go!
離開這，快走！ 你在想什麼，快走！
Rue?
茹？
It's okay. I'm not gonna hurt you.
沒事，我不會傷害你的
You want mine, too?
我的也給你吧？
No, that's okay.
不用了
Here.
給
Thanks.
謝謝
How long was I asleep?
我昏迷多久了？
Couple of days. I changed your leaves twice.
好幾天了，我幫你換了兩次樹葉
Thank you.
謝謝
So what happened while I was out?
我昏迷這幾天都發生什麼了？
The girl from 1 and the boy from 10.
第1區的女孩和第10區的男孩
And the boy from my district?
和我一起來的男孩呢？
Yeah, he's okay. I think he's down by the river.
他沒事，我想他沿著河邊往下遊走了
Is all of that true?
那些都是真的嗎？
What?
什麼？
You and him?
你們倆？
So where are Cato and the others?
卡托和其他人在哪？
They got all their supplies down by the lake.
他們把所有補給品放在河邊
It's piled up in this great big pyramid.
堆成很大的錐型
That sounds tempting.
聽起來很誘人
Now, this green stuff is gonna smoke like crazy,
這些樹枝可以很快的燃燒起來
so as soon as you light it, move on to the next fire.
一旦你點燃它了，就接著去點燃下一堆
Light this one last, and I'll meet you back over there.
點燃最後這堆後，我會在那跟你會合
Right.
好的
And then I'll destroy their stuff while they're chasing us.
然後當他們去抓我們的時候，我會摧毀他們的補給品
We need a signal in case one of us gets held up.
一旦我們當中的一個被抓了，需要一個暗號
Okay. Like what?
好，什麼暗號？
Here. Watch this.
看著
Mockingjays. That's great.
學舌鳥，太棒了
Back home, we use them to signal all the time.
在家的時候，我們一直用它們做暗號
You try.
你來試試
Okay, so if we hear that,
很好，一旦我們聽見這聲音
it means we're okay and we'll be back real soon.
就表示我倆都沒事，很快便會再見面的
We're gonna be okay.
我們會沒事的
Hey, I'll see you for supper.
晚餐見
-Okay-
- 好的
Guys. Guys, look! Over here. Come on, come on. Look!
夥計們，看吶！這呢 過來，看這邊！
Let's go.
我們走
You stay guard and don't move until we can get back.
你要保持警惕在我們回來之前別離開
I want to see if she's gonna figure out this booby trap.
我倒想看看她能否搞定這個陷阱
Yes. It seems they've reburied their mines
是啊，看起來這一大堆好吃的旁邊
around that big pile of goodies.
埋了不少地雷
She's certainly figured it out, hasn't she?
她一定能搞定的，不是麼？
I don't know what happened.
我不知道發生了什麼
- What the hell happened? - I don't know!
- 究竟是怎麼回事？ - 我不知道
Our stuff!
補給品全毀了！
Katniss!
凱特尼斯！
Katniss, help!
凱特尼斯，救命！
Katniss! Help!
凱特尼斯！救救我！
Katniss!
凱特尼斯！
It's okay. It's okay.
沒事了
You're okay. You're okay. You're fine. See?
沒事的，你很好，明白嗎？
It's okay. You're okay.
會好起來的
You're okay. You're okay.
一切都會好的
Did you blow up the food?
你把他們的食物毀掉了嗎？
Every bit of it.
片甲不留
Good.
太好了
You have to win.
你贏定了
Can you sing?
你能唱歌給我聽嗎？
Okay.
好的
Deep in the meadow
在草叢深處
Under the willows
在柳樹下
A bed of grass
草墊床
A soft green pillow
軟軟的綠枕頭
Lay down your head
把頭放上去
and close your eyes
閉上你的眼
And when they open, the sun...
當你睜開眼，陽光……
I'm sorry.
對不起
[DISTRICT 11]
[11區]
Don't kill her. You'll just create a martyr.
別殺她，這樣只能多一個犧牲者而已
Well, it seems we've already got one.
看起來我們已經有一個了
I hear these rumors out of District 11. This could get away from you.
關於11區的傳言我也聽說了 如果按我說的做可以避免把你捲入是非
What do you want?
你想怎麼樣？
You have a lot of anger out there.
那有很多憤怒的群眾
I know you know how to handle a mob. You've done it before.
我想你應該知道如何處理這幫暴徒 之前你也經歷過
If you can't scare them, give them something to root for.
如果你不能嚇跑他們，就支持他們吧
Such as?
比如？
Young love.
浪漫的愛情
So you like an underdog?
你怎麼像個窮鬼一樣？
Everyone likes an underdog.
大家都喜歡窮鬼
I don't.
我不喜歡
Have you been out there? 10? 11? 12?
你去過那嗎？10區？11區？12區？
Not personally. No.
沒去過
Well, I have.
我去過
There are lots of underdogs.
那有很多窮人
Lots of coal, too.
煤也不少
Grow crops, minerals, things we need.
農作物，礦產，都是我們需要的東西
There are lots of underdogs.
窮人很多
And I think if you could see them,
我想如果你看到他們
you would not root for them either.
就不會支持他們了
I like you.
我欣賞你
Be careful.
當心點
Attention, Tributes. Attention.
貢品請注意，貢品請注意
The regulations requiring a single victor have been suspended.
只有1名獲勝者的比賽規則暫定廢除
From now on, two victors may be crowned,
從現在起，允許有兩名勝者
if both originate from the same district.
只要兩人來自於同一區
This will be the only announcement.
僅此通告
Peeta.
皮塔
Oh, my God! Peeta! Peeta!
天吶！皮塔！皮塔！
Hi.
嗨
It's okay.
沒事了
What was it?
怎麼弄的？
A sword.
刀傷
It's bad, huh?
糟透了，不是麼？
It's gonna be fine.
會好起來的
Katniss.
凱特尼斯
- Katniss. - No!
- 凱特尼斯 - 不！
I'm not gonna leave you. I'm not gonna do that.
我不會離開你 再也不會那麼做了
Why not?
為什麼？
Nobody's gonna find you in here.
在這沒人會找到你
They already found me.
他們已經發現我一次了
We'll just get you some medicine.
我們會給你弄些藥
Katniss, I don't get many parachutes.
凱特尼斯，我沒弄到多少降落傘補給
We'll figure something out.
我們會有辦法的
Like what?
比如說？
Something.
會有的
[YOU CALL THAT A KISS? - H]
[這也算接吻嗎？ -黑密斯]
- Medicine? - No. Soup.
- 是藥嗎？ - 不，是湯
I'll do it.
我來餵你吧
That's nice.
味道真好
You fed me once.
曾經你有恩於我
I think about that all the time.
我一直在想
How I tossed you that bread.
我怎麼能把麵包丟給你呢
- Peeta... - I should have gone to you.
- 皮塔 - 我應該把它送給你
I should have just gone out in the rain and...
我應該冒雨走到你面前然後……
You feel hot.
你好像有點發燒
I remember the first time I saw you.
我還記得第一次見到你是什麼樣子
Your hair was in two braids instead of one.
你梳兩條辮子
And I remember when you sang in the music assembly.
我還記得當你在音樂課唱歌的時候
The teacher said,
老師說「誰知道山谷之歌？」 "Who knows The Valley Song?」
And your hand shot straight up.
你第一個把手舉起來
Stop.
別說了
After that, I watched you going home every day.
從那之後，我每天都會看著你回家
Every day-
每天都是
Well, say something.
說點什麼吧
I'm not good at saying something.
我不擅長和別人交流
Then come here.
那就到這來
Please.
來吧
Even if I don't make it...
即使我沒有…
Stop it.
別說了
Attention, Tributes. Attention.
貢品請注意，貢品請注意
Commencing at sunrise, there will be a feast tomorrow
明天日出時分，在豐饒角
at the Cornucopia.
會有一場盛筵
This will be no ordinary occasion.
想參加的話並不輕鬆
Each of you needs something desperately.
你們每個人都要拿出真本事
And we plan to be generous hosts.
我們是很慷慨的
Your medicine.
會有你需要的藥品
You're not going alone.
你別自己去
Yeah? You need it, and you can't walk.
你需要它，你現在無法行走
Katniss, you're not gonna risk your life for me. I'm not gonna let you.
凱特尼斯，別為了我拿自己的性命冒險，我不會讓你去的
You would do it for me. Wouldn't you?
如果換做是你，也會這麼做，不是嗎？
Why are you doing this?
為什麼要這麼做？
Now there's no way I'm letting you go.
現在我更不可能讓你去了
Peeta...
皮塔…
Please.
求你了
Stay.
留下吧
Okay.
好吧
I'll stay.
我不走
Oh, God!
哦，天吶！
Where's lover boy?
你的男朋友呢？
I see. You were gonna help him, right?
我知道了，你是為他而來的，對不對？
Well, that's sweet. You know, it's too bad that you couldn't help your little friend.
太感人了。你知道嗎，救不了你那位小朋友 是多麼糟糕的一件事
That little girl? What was her name again?
她叫什麼來著？
Rue?
茹？
Yeah, well, we killed her.
就是她，是我們殺了她
And now we're gonna kill you.
現在我來幹掉你
You kill her?
你殺了她？
- No! - I heard you!
- 不！ - 我聽見你說的了！
- Cato! Cato! - You said her name!
- 卡托！卡托！ - 你說了她的名字！
You said her name!
是你說的！
Just this time, 12.
就這一次
For Rue.
為了茹
Peeta, I got it. I got the medicine.
皮塔，我找到藥了
- What happened to you? - I'm fine.
- 你怎麼了 - 沒怎麼
No, you're not. What happened?
不，你受傷了，發生什麼了？
The girl from 2, she threw a knife. I'm okay.
2區的女孩，對我丟了一把飛刀，沒事的
You shouldn't have gone. You said you weren't gonna go.
你就不應該去 你說過你不會去的
You got worse.
你的傷好像更糟了
I'm sorry.
對不起
You need some of that, too.
你也需要抹一點
I'm okay.
我沒事
That feels better.
感覺好多了
Okay. Now you.
好的，該你了
- I'm okay. - No, come on, you need it, too.
- 我不用 - 來吧，你也抹點吧
Come on.
來
All right.
好吧
Hi.
嗨
You're so much better.
你痊癒得這麼快
Oh, my God, Peeta.
哦，天吶！皮塔
I hardly feel anything.
我感覺好像沒受過傷一樣
We could go home.
我們能回家了
We could. We're the only team left.
是的，我們是這組裏僅存的兩個人
We know Thresh took off.
我們現在得知斯瑞斯離開了 （註：斯瑞斯，11區男性參賽者， 他能活著的唯一依靠就是一身蠻力）
Cato's gonna be by the Cornucopia.
卡托會去豐饒角那
He's not gonna go someplace he doesn't know.
他不會到自己沒去過的地方
Foxface, she could be anywhere.
福克斯費斯不一定在哪呢 （註：福克斯費斯，5區女性參賽者， 靠頭腦作戰，擅長軍事佈局與策略）
We should probably hunt around here. We don't have any food left.
咱們應該在這附近打獵 帶的食物都吃光了
Okay, I'll take the bow.
好吧，我來射箭吧
I'm just kidding. I'll go pick some stuff.
開玩笑罷了，我去採點果子
Peeta?
皮塔？
Peeta!
皮塔！
Are you okay?
你沒事吧？
- I heard the cannon. I thought... - No.
- 我聽到加農炮的聲音了，我以為… - 不
That's Nightlock, Peeta! You'd be dead in a minute!
那是毒漿果，皮塔！吃它會要了你的命！
I didn't know.
我不知道
You scared me to death. Damn you.
該死的，你差點嚇死我了
I'm sorry.
對不起
I never even knew she was following me.
我還不知道她在一直跟蹤我
She's clever.
她真聰明
Too clever.
聰明極了
- What are you doing? - Maybe Cato likes berries, too.
- 你在幹什麼？ - 也許卡托會喜歡這些漿果
What time is it?
現在幾點了？
A little after noon.
剛到下午
Why is it getting so dark?
為什麼天色這麼黑？
Must be in a hurry to end it.
看來要盡早結束這場爭鬥了
- You ready, Lucia? - Right here, sir.
- 準備好了嗎， 露西婭？ - 在這，先生
Well, that's great.
很好，太棒了
- Now can you put that in the middle? - Sure.
- 可以把它放到競技場嗎？ - 沒問題
That's it. That's excellent.
就是這樣，效果一定不錯
Did you hear that?
你聽見了嗎？
What was that?
那是什麼聲音？
It's the finale.
慘叫
Let's go.
我們走吧
Go.
快跑
Katniss!
凱特尼斯！
Here!
上去！
Go on. Shoot.
來啊，射我啊
Then we both go down and you'd win.
我們倆都掉下去，你就贏了
Go on. I'm dead anyway.
來吧，反正我死定了
I always was, right?
一向如此，對嗎？
I didn't know that till now.
直到現在我才知道
How is that? Is that what they want?
怎麼會這樣呢？這就是他們想要的嗎？
- No. - No, no.
- 不 - 不，不要
I could still do this.
我也可以把他的脖子扭斷的
One more kill.
再殺一個又能怎樣
It's the only thing I know how to do.
這使我唯一知道怎麼做的事
Bring pride to my district.
為我所在地的區域帶來榮耀
Not that it matters.
這並不重要
Please!
求你了！
No!
不！
Attention. Attention, Tributes.
貢品請注意，貢品請注意
There has been a slight rule change.
規則稍有變化
The previous revision,
之前允許同一區域的兩人
allowing for two victors from the same district,
可作為勝者的規則
has been revoked.
已被廢除
Only one victor may be crowned. Good luck.
新規則規定只允許有一名勝者，祝你們好運
And may the odds be ever in your favor.
希望好運永遠站在你這邊
Go ahead.
來吧
One of us should go home.
只有一個人能回家
One of us has to die. They have to have their victor.
必須要有人作出犧牲，他們只要一個勝者
No.
不
They don't.
他們不能這樣
Why should they?
為什麼總任由他們擺佈？
- No! - Trust me.
- 不！ - 相信我
Trust me.
相信我
Together?
一起來？
Together.
一起
Okay.
好的
Stop!
住手！
Ladies and gentlemen, may I present the winners
女士們，先生們，我來介紹一下
of the 74th Annual Hunger Games.
第74屆年度飢餓遊戲的勝者
They're not happy with you.
他們對你並不滿意
Why? Because I didn't die?
為什麼？因為我沒死嗎？
Because you showed them up.
因為你讓他們出醜了
Well, I'm sorry it didn't go the way they planned.
好吧，對不起，我沒按規則辦事
- I'm not very happy with them either. - Katniss!
- 我對他們也不滿意 - 凱特尼斯！
This is serious. Notjust for you.
嚴肅一點，這不只是為了你自己
They don't take these things lightly.
他們不會就這麼輕易罷手的
When they ask, you say you couldn't help yourself.
當他們問你的時候，你就說控制不住自己
You were so in love with this boy
你和這個男孩很恩愛
that the thought of not being with him was unthinkable.
不敢想像沒有他會是什麼樣子
You'd rather die than not be with him. You understand?
如果失去他不如讓我去死，明白嗎？
How did you feel when you found him by that river?
當你在河邊找到他的時候是什麼感覺？
I felt like the happiest person in the world.
感覺我是全世界最幸福的人
I couldn't imagine life without him.
不敢想像沒有他生活會變成什麼樣子
And what about you, Peeta?
你呢，皮塔？
She saved my life.
他救了我一命
We saved each other.
我們拯救了彼此
Ladies and gentlemen, the star-crossed lovers from District 12,
女士們，先生們，第74屆年度飢餓遊戲總冠軍是
this year's victors of the 74th Annual Hunger Games!
來自第12區的倒霉情侶！
Congratulations.
恭喜你們
Thank you.
謝謝
What a lovely pin.
胸針很漂亮
Thank you. It's from my district.
謝謝，這是我們區域的饋贈
They must be very proud of you.
他們一定會為你感到非常驕傲的
So what happens when we get back?
回去了我們會怎麼樣？
I don't know. I guess we try to forget.
不知道，我想我們應該試著忘記這段經歷
I don't want to forget.
我不想忘掉